<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Glossary of Heritrix Terms</title>
    <author email="stack at archive dot org">St.Ack</author>
    <revision>$Id$</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Glossary">


    <subsection name="Checkpointing">
        <p>Heritrix currently has no checkpointing facility. However, our
        conception of what we need is heavily influenced by what Mercator
        provided. In <a 
        href="http://citeseer.nj.nec.com/najork01highperformance.html">one
        of the papers on Mercator</a> it is described this way:
<source>Checkpointing is an important part of any long-running process such as
a web crawl. By checkpointing we mean writing a representation of the crawler's
state to stable storage that, in the event of a failure, is sufficient to allow
the crawler to recover its state by reading the checkpoint and to resume
crawling from the exact state it was in at the time of the checkpoint. By this
definition, in the event of a failure, any work performed after the most recent
checkpoint is lost, but none of the work up to the most recent checkpoint. In
Mercator, the frequency with which the background thread performs a checkpoint
is user-configurable; we typically checkpoint anywhere from 1 to 4 times per
day.</source></p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Frontier">
        <p>A Frontier is a plug-able module in Heritrix that maintains the
        internal state of the crawl.  See
        the <a href="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/index.html">URIFrontier
        Interface</a> javadoc comments for more on what a frontier does.
        </p>
    </subsection>


<subsection name="Host">

<p>A host can serve multiple domains or a single domain can be served by 
multiple hosts.  For our purposes so far, 
<i>host</i> == <i>hostname in URI</i> 
DNS is not considered; it is volatile and may be unavailable.
So when we get the URIs...
<source>
    http://www.example.com
    http://search.example.com
    http://201.199.7.15
</source>
...even if they all point to the 201.199.7.15 IP, they are 3 different logical
hosts (at the level of the URI/HTTP protocol). Conformant
HTTP proxies behave similarly, we think, even if they know www.example.com ==
201.199.7.15, they will not consider them interchangeable.
</p>

<p>This is not ideal for politeness where we'd want politeness rules to 
apply to the physical host rather than the logical.</p>

<p><a href="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlHost.html">CrawlHost</a> is used to represent our notion of a <i>Host</i>
(whereas <a href="http://crawler.archive.org/apidocs/org/archive/crawler/datamodel/CrawlServer.html">CrawlServer</a> is used to represent a
<i>Server</i> on that host: e.g. there would be a <code>CrawlHost</code>
for yahoo.com and one <code>CrawlServer</code> instance for the yahoo.com:80
and another for yahoo.com:443.
</p>

</subsection>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>
