<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Glossary of Heritrix Terms</title>
    <author email="stack at archive dot org">St.Ack</author>
    <revision>$Id$</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Glossary">
    <subsection name="Checkpointing">
        <p>Heritrix currently has no checkpointing facility. However, our
        conception of what we need is heavily influenced by what Mercator
        provided. In <a 
        href="http://citeseer.nj.nec.com/najork01highperformance.html">one
        of the papers on Mercator</a> it is described this way:
<source>Checkpointing is an important part of any long-running process such as
a web crawl. By checkpointing we mean writing a representation of the crawler's
state to stable storage that, in the event of a failure, is sufficient to allow
the crawler to recover its state by reading the checkpoint and to resume
crawling from the exact state it was in at the time of the checkpoint. By this
definition, in the event of a failure, any work performed after the most recent
checkpoint is lost, but none of the work up to the most recent checkpoint. In
Mercator, the frequency with which the background thread performs a checkpoint
is user-configurable; we typically checkpoint anywhere from 1 to 4 times per
day.</source></p>
    </subsection>



    <subsection name="Transclusion">
    <p>Heritrix has a transclusion filter.  A 
        <b>transclusion</i> is the reuse in whole or in part of another node in
        one node's rendering. That is, one node including another node when it
        is being displayed. A transclusion is different from pure copying,
        however, in that only a reference to the foreign material is stored.
        The reader's client software is expected to fetch the foreign material
        and place it inline with the main material.  For instance, if I wrote
        a report on wheat farming and I was talking
        about the relative price of wheat around the world, I'd want to place a
        chart of those prices on my site. Instead of creating the chart myself,
        I could just transclude the chart from the World Trade Organization
        directly in my report.  Definition from <a 
       href="http://www.usemod.com/cgi-bin/mb.pl?TransClusion">TransClusion</a>.
        </p>
        <p>In the heritrix context, the transclusion filter makes 
        judgements based on dynamic counters keeping account of
        embeded/included links.</p>
    </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
