<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Known Limitations</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>$Date$</date>

    <authorgroup>
      <corpauthor>Internet Archive</corpauthor>
    </authorgroup>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This document lists known limitations by version number.
    It includes user and developer notes.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="1_0_0">
    <title>Heritrix 1.0.0</title>

    <sect2 id="upper_bounds">
      <title>Crawl Size Upper Bounds</title>

      <para>Heritrix 1.0.0 uses disk-based queues to hold any number of
pending URIs bounded only by available disk space, but still relies on
in-memory structures to efficiently track all discovered hosts and
previously-scheduled URIs.  Crawls whose total scheduled URIs or discovered
hosts exhaust all available memory will trigger out-of-memory errors, which
freeze a crawl at the point of the error.</para>

<para>With the default settings, and an assignment of a 256MB Java heap to the
Heritrix process, crawling which discovers up to 10 000 hosts, and schedules
over 6 000 000 URIs, should be possible. Discovery of higher numbers of
URIs/hosts will likely trigger out-of-memory problems unless a larger java heap
was assigned at startup.</para>

<para>Broad crawls -- those using the BroadScope or ranging over domains with
many subdomains -- can easily and quickly exceed these parameters. Thus broad
crawls in Heritrix 1.0.0 are not recommended, except for experimental
purposes.</para>

<para>Narrower crawls, restricted to specific hosts or domains a limited number
of subdomains, can run for a week or more, collecting millions of resources.
Larger heaps can allow crawls to run into the tens of millions of collected
URIS, and tens of thousands of discovered hosts.</para>

<para>An experimental alternate Frontier, the DiskIncludedFrontier, is also
available via the 'Modules' crawl configuration tab. It uses a capped amount of
memory plus disk storage to remember any number of scheduled URIs, but its
performance is poor and it has not received the same testing as our default
Frontier. The memory cost of additional discovered hosts continues to rise
without limit when using a DiskIncludedFrontier.</para>

<para>Future versions of Heritrix will include other frontier implementations
allowing larger and unbounded crawls with minimal performance penalties.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="958055">
      <title><ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/?func=detail&amp;aid=958055&amp;group_id=73833&amp;atid=539099">[ 958055 ] Seed ConcurrentModificationException</ulink>
      </title>

      <para>Its possible to get ConcurrentModificationsException editing options on 
      a running crawl.</para>
      <sect3><title>Workaround</title>
        <para>Pause the crawl when making changes to crawl options.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="984390">
      <title><ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/?func=detail&amp;aid=984390&amp;group_id=73833&amp;atid=539099">[ 984390 ] Build fails: "rws" mode and Mac OS X interact badly</ulink></title>

    <para>On macintoshes and linux kernel version 2.6, heritrix fails to build
    (unit tests fail).</para>
      <sect3><title>Workaround</title>
        <para>See issue, <ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/?func=detail&amp;aid=984390&amp;group_id=73833&amp;atid=539099">[ 984390 ] Build fails: "rws" mode and Mac OS X interact badly</ulink>, for source code workaround edit.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>


    <sect2 id="955975">
      <title><ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=955975&amp;group_id=73833&amp;atid=539099">[ 955975 ] Build fails: JVM and kernel 2.6+ (Was 2 tests fail...)</ulink></title>

    <para>Heritrix fails to build on linux kernel 2.6.</para>
      <sect3><title>Workaround</title>
        <para>Build fails unless you use a JDK in advance of pedigree 
        1.5 beta 2.  See <ulink
        url="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=955975&amp;group_id=73833&amp;atid=539099">[ 955975 ] Build fails: JVM and kernel 2.6+ (Was 2 tests fail...)</ulink> and 
        <ulink url="#984390">above</ulink>.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    </sect1>
</article>
