<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Heritrix user manual</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Heritrix is the Internet Archive's open-source, extensible,
    web-scale, archival-quality web crawler. This document explains how to
    create, configure and run crawls using it.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Installing and launching Heritrix</title>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Web based user interface</title>

    <para>After Heritrix has been launched from the command line, the web
    based user interface (WUI) becomes accessible.</para>

    <para>The path to it printed out on the console from which the program was
    launched (typically http://&lt;host&gt;:8080/admin/).</para>

    <para>The WUI is password protected. The username is currently hardcoded
    to 'admin' with the default password of 'letmein'. The password can be
    specified at startup and users are encouraged to change it. The currently
    valid password will be printed out to the console along with the
    path.</para>

    <para>The WUI can then be accessed via any browser. While we've
    endeavoured to make certain that it functions in all recent browsers,
    Mozilla 5+ is recommended. IE 6+ should also work without problems.</para>

    <para>The inital login page takes the standard username/password
    comibnation discuessed before. In addition users can opt to have the WUI
    remember their login by checking the appropriate box. If that is done then
    the login information will be stored in a cookie and read from it during
    future login attempts. If this option is not checked then the login is
    only valid as long as the server's session. Once it times you, the user
    will need to login again.</para>

    <caution>
      <para>The access control to the WUI is not encrypted! Passwords will be
      submitted over the network in plain text.</para>
    </caution>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>A quick guide to running your first crawl job</title>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Creating jobs and profiles</title>

    <para>In order to run a crawl a configuration must be created that defines
    it. In Heritrix such a configuration is called a Crawl job.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Crawl job</title>

      <para>A Crawl job encompassses the configurations needed to run a single
      crawl. It also contains some additional elements such as logs, status
      etc. </para>

      <para>Once logged onto the WUI new jobs can be created by going to the
      <emphasis>Jobs</emphasis> tab. Once the Jobs page loads users can create
      jobs by choosing of the following three options:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Create new crawl job</emphasis></para>

          <para>This option creates a new crawl job based on the currently set
          default profile.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Create new crawl job based on a
          profile</emphasis></para>

          <para>This option allows the user to create a job by basing it on
          one of the profiles offered up.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Create new crawl job based on an
          existing job</emphasis></para>

          <para>This option allows the user to create a job by basing it on
          any existing job, regardless of wether it has been crawled or not.
          Can be usefull for repeating crawls..</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Options 2 and 3 will display a list of availible options.
      Initially there is only one profile and no existing jobs.</para>

      <para>As should be clear by now, all crawl jobs are created by basing
      them on profiles (see next chapter) or existing jobs. </para>

      <para>Once the proper profile/job has been chosen to base the new job
      one a simple page will appear asking for the new jobs:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis></para>

          <para>The name must only contain letters, numbers, dash (-) and
          underscore (_). No other characters are allowed. This name will be
          used to identify the crawl in the UI but it need not be unique. The
          name can not be changed later</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></para>

          <para>A short description of the job. This can be edited
          later.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Seeds</emphasis></para>

          <para>The seed URLs to use for the job. This list can be edited
          later along with the general configurations.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Below these input fields there are several buttons. The last one
      Submit job will immediately submit the job and (assuming that it's
      properly configured) it will be ready to run (see <xref
      linkend="running" />). The other buttons will take the user</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Profile</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Configuring jobs and profiles</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Settings</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Modules</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Filters</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Credentials</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Overrides</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Refinements</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="running">
    <title>Running a job</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Console</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Pending jobs</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Monitoring a running job</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Analysis of jobs</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Completed jobs</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Logs</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Reports</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Outside the user interface</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>